Teaching Support Staff Union fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Teaching Support Staff Union fonds
1967 - 1994
F-38
Q106068456
2.25 m of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Teaching Support Staff Union
The Teaching Support Staff Union is the representative bargaining agent for Teaching Assistants, Tutor Markers, Language Instructors and Sessional Instructors at Simon Fraser University. The union negotiates terms and conditions of work, rates of pay, benefits and grievance procedures in a Collective Agreement with the University.
In 1971 graduate students organized the Graduate Student Union, an association that worked to improve teaching and research conditions. The GSU was inactive after 1974 but the discussion it had initiated regarding unionization continued until 1976 when twelve graduate students held a union organizational meeting in September of that year. They proposed affiliation with the Association of University and College Employees (AUCE) rather than the Canadian Union of Public Employees or the University of Toronto based Graduate Assistants' Association. The Teaching Support Staff Union, as it would be named, favored AUCE because of its relative smallness, democratic structure, local autonomy, strong representation of women's employment rights, and the established presence at SFU, since 1974, of AUCE Local 2 for office, clerical and technical staff. Accordingly, the TSSU received its charter as AUCE Local 6 on September 10, 1976.
The TSSU took additional steps to establish themselves as a legal entity under the British Columbia Labour Code. By April 1978 the TSSU had signed over 50% of the bargaining unit into the union. It then applied to the Labour Relations Board for a certification vote to make the TSSU the representative body for the bargaining unit. Before the vote could be held, however, the LRB conducted a hearing to define the membership of the bargaining unit, which had been disputed by the University. Following an LRB ruling in TSSU's favor, the certification vote was finally held in November 1978. The vote was positive despite an effort by some Language Assistants to have the LRB exclude them from the bargaining unit and the vote. The LRB certified the union on December 13, 1978.
In January 1979 the union began bargaining with the University for a first collective agreement. The TSSU and the University administration negotiated each article individually and resolved impasses through mediation. During negotiations, the TSSU successfully complained to the LRB that the University had violated Section 51 of the Labour Code by withholding an annual pay increase. The first Collective Agreement was signed by both sides on July 1, 1980, and has been renegotiated from time to time.
TSSU supported its sister local, AUCE 2, during the latter's strike in 1979. In 1983 and 1984, TSSU joined other campus unions in Operation Solidarity, a province-wide organization opposed to Premier Bennett's Social Credit restraint legislation.
TSSU remained as the last independent local of AUCE until the latter's dissolution in the early 1990s. Still functioning as an independent union, TSSU operates under a constitution and bylaws as a membership-driven organization. Union policy, bargaining positions, and the election of union officers and salaried officers are decided by the membership through meetings, mail-in ballots, and referenda. Departmental stewards serve as immediate contacts for TSSU members. In addition, a number of standing committees conduct on-going business and help direct the executive and general membership. Ad hoc committees have functioned from time to time.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on the name of the body.
The fonds consists of records created and received in the course of the formation, establishment and operation of the union, primarily during the period 1976-1987. The records reflect the initial drive to charter, organize and certify the union; the internal administration of the union, including elections and finance; negotiations with the administration to establish and renew contracts; efforts to maintain, expand, represent and inform the membership; participation in the provincial organization of the Association of University and College Employees and cooperation with other AUCE locals, and other unions; and involvement in industrial action. Also included are records of the Graduate Students' union, a forerunner, though not direct predecessor, of TSSU. The records include the charter and bylaws; committee agendas and minutes; financial statements; correspondence; membership lists; election materials; reports; negotiation minutes and collective agreements; mediation and hearing records; convention minutes; strike materials; publications and publicity materials. The records as received had no obvious overall arrangement. Duplicate material has been removed where practicable, but the mixed nature of the files requires researchers to be prepared to search for records on matters of interest.
The titles and arrangement of series were provided by the archivist. Included in the appropriate series are files that were marked as belonging to certain TSSU organizers and staff members (S. Marria, M. Pujol, and R. Wiseman). These files were intermingled with the other office files when received.
Association of University and College Employees, Local 2; Graduate Student Union; Labour
The records were received in a number of accessions from the union's office between 1986 and 1996.
All accessions have been processed as of September 2002. Further accruals are expected.
Consult the inventories of Canadian Union of Public Employees Local 3338 fonds, which includes AUCE Local 2 (SFU), and the Heather Raven fonds. See also the inventory of the Simon Fraser University Non-Faculty Teachers' Association F-68. Additionally, see the SORWUC fonds at the University of British Columbia.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
File lists are available.
- Graduate Student Union, 1970 - 1974; F-38-1; 9 cm of textual records
  The Graduate Student Union (GSU) was active from 1971 to 1974, campaigning on behalf of all SFU graduate students for reasonable fees, income support, office facilities, better representation, and a Graduate Appeals Board; for teaching assistants in particular, it also sought a more advantageous payment system and a training program. It was successful with fees and training as well as some individual grievances, but by early 1974 its limited achievements persuaded the executive to canvas support for a formal, legal unionization of teaching assistants. These efforts came to fruition in 1976 with the establishment of the Teaching Support Staff Union (TSSU).
  published
  Series consists of records relating to the operation of this predecessor of the TSSU. Activities documented include the establishment of the GSU, negotiation of responsibility for graduate matters with Simon Fraser Student Society, organizing meetings, membership expansion, researching current graduate conditions and proposing improvements through reports and lobbying, participation in university committees, liaison with other university graduate student organizations, and publicizing efforts through newsletters. Records include GSU statutes, policies and history; extensive correspondence including legal advice on the GSU's status; meeting notices, agendas, notes, and accounts; membership and election material; reference and research sources; reports and papers (e.g. on the need for a teaching assistants' union); and newsletters.
  - GSU correspondence 1/3, 1971 - 1972; F-38-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 38-1)
    Textual records
    Restricted in part
  - GSU correspondence 2/3, 1972; F-38-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 38-1)
    Open
  - GSU correspondence 3/3, 1972 - 1973; F-38-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 38-1)
  - GSU correspondence and reports, 1972 - 1974; F-38-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 38-1)
  - GSU newsletters, meeting notices and agenda, 1971 - 1974; F-38-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 38-1)
  - GSU recognition initiative, 1971 - 1972; F-38-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 38-1)
  - Graduate Appeals Board Proposal, 1970 - 1974; F-38-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 38-1)
  - Teaching Assistants Union Inquiry, 1972 - 1974; F-38-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 38-1)
- Organization and certification, 1973 - 1994; F-38-2; 16 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the formation, chartering, growth, and official recognition of AUCE Local 6/TSSU. Activities documented include the charter application; early organizing, steering, executive and membership committee meetings; the identification, lobbying, and processing of new bargaining unit members; training departmental representatives; publicizing union activities; informing departments of the implications of unionization; researching and preparing submissions for Labour Relations Board Certification hearings; attending and recording LRB hearings; and pursuing members' grievances through LRB hearings. Records include the AUCE 6 charter and by-laws; meeting agendas and minutes; membership publicity and correspondence (including correspondence with TSSU opponents); instructional materials; TSSU publications, including AUCE and TSSU: memoirs of a feminist union 1972-1993; anti-TSSU publicity and petitions; LRB certification drafts and submissions; LRB hearing transcripts (re Labour Code sections 42 [bargaining unit], 51 [certification] and 52 [decertification]) and related correspondence; and LRB grievance submissions, evidence and correspondence.
  - TSSU and 1976 Poly Party strike, 1976 - 1977; F-38-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 38-1)
    Open, reading room
    Access review (Feb. 13, 2023): some records flagged for non-sensitive personal information (contact information); reading room access only.
  - Charter, early minutes, by-laws, 1976 - 1992; F-38-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 38-1)
  - Authorizations to receive members, 1976 - 1978; F-38-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 38-1)
    Open, no restrictions
  - Minutes, organizing phase, 1976 - 1979; F-38-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 38-2)
    Access review (Mar 1, 2023) – File is open, no restricted information identified.
  - Organizing minutes, notes (S. Marria file), 1977 - 1979; F-38-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 38-2)
  - Committees minutes, notes, 1978; F-38-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 38-2)
  - Organizing publicity, notes, 1977 - 1980; F-38-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 38-2)
    Open with enclosures
    Access review (Mar 1, 2023) – The bulk of the file is open for reading room access. However, it includes two documents that contain the personal information of identifiable individuals (student number, individual’s own views or opinions, medical history). Restricted documents have been removed (enclosed); the rest of the file is open. Enclosed records may be accessed under a Research Agreement; consult the reference archivist for more information.
  - Background papers, minutes, notes (s.42 hearing), 1977 - 1978; F-38-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 38-2)
  - M. Pujol/Economics Dept chair meeting notes, 1978; F-38-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 38-2)
    Access review (May 3, 2023) – File is open, no restricted information identified.
  - Early organization and opposition, 1977 - 1979; F-38-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 38-2)
    Access review (Apr 21, 2023) – File includes records that contain some individuals' personal contact information. File can be accessed in the Archives' reading room.
  - Internal (AUCE) report, 1979; F-38-2-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 38-2)
  - TSSU opposition (Ad Hoc Group), 1979 - 1980; F-38-2-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 38-2)
  - Certification application, correspondence (S. Marria file), 1976 - 1980; F-38-2-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 38-2)
    Access review (Apr 21, 2023) – File is open, no restricted information identified.
  - Labour Relations Board correspondence on certification, s.51, 1977 - 1980; F-38-2-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 38-2)
    Pending review
  - Certification hearing transcripts, 1978; F-38-2-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 38-2)
  - De-certification correspondence, 1978 - 1979; F-38-2-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 38-2)
    Access review (Apr 24, 2023) – File is open, no restricted information identified.
  - De-certification (s.52(2)) vote, hearing, 1980; F-38-2-0-0-17 (Archival box - small 38-19)
  - Organizing reports, 1980 - 1981; F-38-2-0-0-18 (Archival box - small 38-19)
    Access review (Apr 19, 2023) – The bulk of the file is open. However, it includes a small number of documents (3) that contain the personal information of identifiable individuals (individual’s own views or opinions, third party opinions about individual). Restricted documents have been removed; the rest of the file is open. Enclosed records may be accessed under a Research Agreement; consult the reference archivist for more information.
  - TSSU history, publications received, [ca 1973] - 1994; F-38-2-0-0-19 (Archival box - small 38-19)
- Collective Agreement negotiations and issues, 1967 - 1993; F-38-3; 81 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the development, agreement and renewal of contracts between SFU and the TSSU. Activities documented include preparatory research by the TSSU contract committee; article by article negotiation meetings between the administration and union; LRB mediation hearings (re e.g. alleged violations of section 51 and 61 freezes on working conditions); ratification ballots of the union membership; and the implementation and monitoring of the completed agreements. Records include comparative tables of articles from similar agreements at other Canadian universities; workshop and seminar notes; union and administration drafts of contract articles; transcripts and minutes of negotiation meetings (some from identified personal files); administration/union correspondence; mediation applications and notices; draft and signed copies of final agreements; letters of agreement; ballot notices, instructions and results sheets; press announcements; and implementation documents (e.g. pay schedules) and correspondence.
  - 4% issue, 1979; F-38-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 38-3)
  - Teaching assistant proposed rates, 4% issue, 1974 - 1979; F-38-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 38-3)
  - 4% hearing transcripts (S. Marria file), 1979; F-38-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 38-3)
  - 4% hearing documents (S. Marria file), 1976 - 1979; F-38-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 38-3)
  - Sect. 51 and 61 (including 4%) evidence (S. Marria file), 1967 - 1979; F-38-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 38-3)
  - 4% hearing documents (S. Marria file), 1977 - 1978; F-38-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 38-3)
  - LRB decision (4% issue), 1979 - 1980; F-38-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 38-3)
  - English 010 sessional instructor hearing, 1980; F-38-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 38-3)
  - English 010 hearing exhibits, 1980; F-38-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 38-3)
  - English 010 hearing transcripts, 1980; F-38-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 38-3)
  - English 010 meetings minutes, 1980; F-38-3-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 38-3)
  - English 010 arbitration and decision, 1980; F-38-3-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 38-3)
  - First contract negotiations: questionnaires, 1979; F-38-3-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 38-4)
  - First contract negotiations: correspondence, notes, 1979 - 1980; F-38-3-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 38-4)
  - First contract negotiations: miscellaneous research, 1979; F-38-3-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 38-4)
  - First contract negotiations: job descriptions, 1979 - 1980; F-38-3-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 38-4)
  - First contract negotiations: remuneration, 1979 - 1980; F-38-3-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 38-4)
  - First contract negotiations: benefits research, 1979 - 1980; F-38-3-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 38-4)
  - First contract negotiations: early draft 1/2, 1979 - 1980; F-38-3-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 38-5)
  - First contract negotiations: early draft 2/2, 1979 - 1980; F-38-3-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 38-5)
  - First contract negotiations: comparative material 1/2, 1976 - 1980; F-38-3-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 38-5)
  - First contract negotiations: comparative material 2/2, 1976 - 1980; F-38-3-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 38-5)
  - First contract negotiations: copies of articles 1/2, 1979 - 1980; F-38-3-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 38-5)
  - First contract negotiations: copies of articles 2/2, 1979 - 1980; F-38-3-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 38-5)
  - First contract negotiations: committee proposals (M. Pujol file), 1977 - 1979; F-38-3-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 38-6)
  - First contract negotiations: draft articles (M. Pujol file), 1979; F-38-3-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 38-6)
  - First contract negotiations: grievance article (M. Pujol file), 1979; F-38-3-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 38-6)
  - First contract negotiations: working papers (R. Wiseman file), 1979 - 1981; F-38-3-0-0-28 (Archival box - standard 38-6)
  - First contract negotiations: draft articles (S. Marria file), 1979; F-38-3-0-0-29 (Archival box - standard 38-6)
  - First contract negotiations: correspondence (S. Marria file), 1979 - 1980; F-38-3-0-0-30 (Archival box - standard 38-6)
  - First contract negotiations: notes (S. Marria file), 1979; F-38-3-0-0-31 (Archival box - standard 38-6)
  - First contract negotiations: research (S. Marria file), 1979; F-38-3-0-0-32 (Archival box - standard 38-6)
  - First contract negotiations: legal committee (S. Marria file), 1979; F-38-3-0-0-33 (Archival box - standard 38-6)
  - First contract negotiations: faculty materials, 1977 - 1979; F-38-3-0-0-34 (Archival box - standard 38-6)
  - First contract negotiations: application for mediator, 1980; F-38-3-0-0-35 (Archival box - standard 38-7)
  - First contract negotiations: mediation notice, 1980; F-38-3-0-0-36 (Archival box - standard 38-7)
  - First contract negotiations: mediation transcript, 1980; F-38-3-0-0-37 (Archival box - standard 38-7)
  - First contract negotiations: mediation 1/2 (S. Marria file), 1979 - 1980; F-38-3-0-0-38 (Archival box - standard 38-7)
  - First contract negotiations: mediation 2/2 (S. Marria file), 1979 - 1980; F-38-3-0-0-39 (Archival box - standard 38-7)
  - First contract negotiations: mediation: costing of offer, 1980; F-38-3-0-0-40 (Archival box - standard 38-7)
  - First contract negotiations: mediation: articles, correspondence, 1979 - 1980; F-38-3-0-0-41 (Archival box - standard 38-7)
  - First contract negotiations: language instructor article, 1980; F-38-3-0-0-42 (Archival box - standard 38-7)
  - First contract negotiations: initialed contract, 1980; F-38-3-0-0-43 (Archival box - standard 38-7)
  - First contract negotiations: contract ratification, 1980; F-38-3-0-0-44 (Archival box - standard 38-7)
  - First contract negotiations: ratification vote, 1980; F-38-3-0-0-45 (Archival box - standard 38-7)
  - First contract negotiations: implementation, 1980; F-38-3-0-0-46 (Archival box - standard 38-7)
  - First contract negotiations: minutes 1/2, 1979; F-38-3-0-0-47 (Archival box - standard 38-8)
  - First contract negotiations: minutes 2/2, 1979; F-38-3-0-0-48 (Archival box - standard 38-8)
  - First contract negotiations: minutes and documents, 1979; F-38-3-0-0-49 (Archival box - standard 38-8)
  - Graduate student stipend, 1981 - 1982; F-38-3-0-0-50 (Archival box - standard 38-8)
  - Second contract negotiations: proposals, 1982; F-38-3-0-0-51 (Archival box - standard 38-8)
  - Second contract negotiations: communications, 1982; F-38-3-0-0-52 (Archival box - standard 38-9)
  - Second contract negotiations: signed contract, 1982 - 1983; F-38-3-0-0-53 (Archival box - standard 38-9)
  - Second contract negotiations: ratification vote, 1982; F-38-3-0-0-54 (Archival box - standard 38-9)
  - Later contract negotiations 1/2, 1985 - 1987; F-38-3-0-0-55 (Archival box - standard 38-9)
  - Later contract negotiations 2/2, 1985 - 1987; F-38-3-0-0-56 (Archival box - standard 38-9)
  - Collective agreements, 1983 - 1993; F-38-3-0-0-57 (Archival box - standard 38-9)
- Executive Committee elections and minutes, 1978 - 1983; F-38-4; 16 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the election and business of the executive committee. Activities documented include the nomination and election of committee members; committee discussions, decisions and actions; and executive correspondence. Records include nomination calls and notices; candidate biographies and statements; ballot instructions, forms and result sheets; minutes (1980-81 only); telegrams and letters concerning union business to members, the university administration, and other unions.
  - Executive election, 1981; F-38-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 38-9)
  - Executive election, 1982; F-38-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 38-9)
  - Executive election, 1983; F-38-4-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 38-9)
  - Executive elections, dues increase referendum, 1980; F-38-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 38-9)
  - Dues increase referendum, 1982; F-38-4-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 38-9)
  - Committee meetings: notes (M. Pujol file), 1978; F-38-4-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 38-9)
  - Committees: minutes, 1981; F-38-4-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 38-9)
  - Executive working papers, 1980 - 1981; F-38-4-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 38-10)
  - Executive diary, 1981 - 1982; F-38-4-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 38-10)
  - Executive policy decisions, 1982 - 1983; F-38-4-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 38-10)
  - Organizers' reports, 1980 - 1981; F-38-4-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 38-10)
  - Staff coordinator (R. Wiseman file), 1981 - 1982; F-38-4-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 38-10)
  - Correspondence with SFU administration, 1978 - 1982; F-38-4-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 38-10)
  - General correspondence, 1978 - 1981; F-38-4-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 38-10)
- Membership, 1978 - 1980; F-38-5; 4 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the recruitment and maintenance of an active membership. Activities documented include the recruitment of new members, the maintenance of a current membership file, and communication with members. Records include lists of bargaining unit members and teaching assistant appointments, and some correspondence.
  - Appointment lists and notes, 1978 - 1980; F-38-5-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 38-10)
  - Membership lists (S. Marria file), 1979; F-38-5-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 38-10)
  - Membership correspondence, 1979 - 1980; F-38-5-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 38-10)
- Stewards' reports, 1976 - 1983; F-38-6; 5 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the work of the TSSU's departmental representatives, and the work of chief stewards. Activities documented include the training of stewards, publicizing of stewards' activity, and the chief stewards' supervision of stewards' work. Records include lists of stewards, stewards' bulletins, reports of chief stewards to the executive and membership, training materials, correspondence and notices.
  - Stewards' bulletins, 1980 - 1983; F-38-6-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 38-11)